<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Micrologia Characters, or essayes, of persons, trades, and places, offered to the city and country. By R.M.</title>
            <author>R. M., fl. 1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1629</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06692</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17146</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102521</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838298</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838298</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2672</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06692)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2672)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1108:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Micrologia Characters, or essayes, of persons, trades, and places, offered to the city and country. By R.M.</title>
                  <author>R. M., fl. 1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[56] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T.C[otes] for Michael Sparke, dwelling at the blue Bible in Greene Arbor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1629.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Characters.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-D.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2672:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2672:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>MJCROLOGJA.</hi> CHARACTERS, <hi>OR</hi> ESSAYES, Of Perſons, Trades, and Places, <hi>offered to the City and Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By R. M.</p>
            <figure>
               <q>HEB DDIEV HEB DDIM</q>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Thomas Cotes</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>T. C.</hi> for <hi>Michael Sparke,</hi> dwelling at the blue Bible in <hi>Green <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 1629.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2672:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2672:2"/>
            <head>The Authors caueatory <hi>Epiſtle to the vnderſtanding</hi> Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ntelligent and indifferent Readers: The frequent vſe of new Bookes ſhould not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be a meanes to conſerue in memory all materiall occurrences; but likewiſe to preſerue for poſterity ſuch Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes of remarkable preſcription, as might eaſily induce (with an vntyred de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light) the mind of the Peruſer. My ſelfe therefore (hauing in the ſmall iournall of my life beene acquainted with ſundry paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in the world) ſhal fairely hope theſe collections to my Country men, will not proue altogether fruitleſſe. The worke in it ſelfe is of no great ſubſtance, not much
<pb facs="tcp:2672:3"/>Satyricall nor Criticall; it onely glances, like the dogs of <hi>Nilus,</hi> taking a lap here and there, and not dwelling long vpon any ſubiect. And becauſe many men, are leſſe offenſiuely reprehended by a conceited ieſting reproofe, then a ſerious; I haue adapted it in the way of Characters, with a Language of ſutable familiarity. They may haply appeare at firſt view a meere congested Chaos of confuſed Chimer as, the Ideas or fantaſmas of an Epidemicke Braine; yet on receipt of the leaſt warmth from the Sun-beames of your fauourable opinions, they ſhall eaſily diſsipate all foggy miſts of erronious miſpriſion, and be real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly clarified in your conſiderate cenſure; for though you may deeme them ſomewhat promiſcuouſly handled; I can well aſſure you my meaning herein was more metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall. That I preſent you with no curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pourtrait of Coſmographicall or Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nologicall relation, my ſlender reading in Hiſtory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> leſſe iudgement in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicks may eaſily approue. Onely I
<pb facs="tcp:2672:3"/>offer at the ſhrine of your ſerious conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, this ſmall peece of Charactery, compriſing the Natures, Arts, Humors, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd diſpoſitions of men. For which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and your greater contentments I haue madly rambled through Court, City Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Vniuerſity, &amp;c If in the due forme of a Character, I haue either ouer roued, flowne wide, or fallen ſhort, it's not vnlike you may impute it to my folly of precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. In this (I excuſiuely make anſwer.) I ſhall not vnfitly reſemble the Painter, who being to figure forth the fury of a mad dogge, the better to expreſſe it, ſtood long curiouſly pidling about the froth or fome iſſuing from his mouth; but finding nothing frame fitly to his intention; raſhly takes vp his pencill, daſhes it againſt the Picture, minding to ſpoyle it: howbeit this ſudden Accident preuailed to make his worke more excellent. So haply may I in theſe ſudden Touches pencill out theſe meane Characters with a more liuely tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, than if I had beene tediouſly curious
<pb facs="tcp:2672:4"/>in contriuing, or vainly vainglorious to embeliſh them with the quaint eare-hony of finest elocution. The world you know is at this time oppreſſed with nothing more then the Preſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> euery one ſtriuing to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dewie Quinteſſence of his braine, through the Limbecke of inuention. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the rest, you ſee, I haue not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſequeſtred my ſelfe; but ſet apart ſome time from matters more ſerious, to collect ſuch ſimples as may extract from my iuyce-barren Quill ſome few drops of your deſired approbation. If I may be fate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt ſo fairely, I ſhall futurely be encourae ged to exemplifie theſe in a choycer ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or amplifie to a competent number others, with a more pleaſing variety. In the meane time for my preſent percloſe and to ſtop the mouth of malicious malignitie, who may without cauſe be exceptious: I onely alleage this, I haue not ſearched deeply into any mans matters, a little I confeſſe I haue touched their manners, and perhaps ſtarted their humors; which
<pb facs="tcp:2672:4"/>if it proue currant to the curteous, I minde not the captious. But if it bee generally miſlikt, as not anſwering your expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; I conclude thus, if you be ſory it is no better, you may be glad it is no longer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Obſequious to your contentm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nts,</hi> R. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:2672:5"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 A fantaſticke Taylor.</item>
               <item>2 A Player.</item>
               <item>3 A Shooe-maker.</item>
               <item>4 A Rope-maker.</item>
               <item>5 A Smith.</item>
               <item>6 A Tobacconiſt.</item>
               <item>7 A Cunning woman.</item>
               <item>8 A Cobler.</item>
               <item>9 A Tooth-Drawer.</item>
               <item>10 A Tinker.</item>
               <item>11 A Fidler.</item>
               <item>12 A Cunning Horſe courſer.</item>
               <item>13 Bethlem.</item>
               <item>14 Ludgate.</item>
               <item>15 Bridewell.</item>
               <item>16 New-gate.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2672:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Characters, OR Witty deſcriptions of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry <hi>perſons, and places,</hi> their qualities, and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> A fantaſticke Taylor.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>S a tenth part of the Bom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſt that goes to the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tting forth of a Man; and of himſelfe could not ſubſiſt, but by being adiunct to the reſt of his Regiment. He is commonly the Fore-part or Facing of many Men in the World; when a faire Suit, of his
<pb facs="tcp:2672:6"/>owne making, and the neweſt edition, preſuppoſes a Shirt ſemblable; yet oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſits neerer the Skinne; ſo ſit, ſo punctuall, as ſcarſely admits any ſhifting Inſertion. His Art in Numbers is not much fluent; yet in way of Subſtraction you may haply finde him dexterious. His dealing conſiſts not much in Weight; but in the Weight of his preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing-Iron, vnder whoſe Tyranny, you ſhall perceiue no ſmall ſhrinking. Onely for Meaſure hee improues himſelfe no niggard, but rather cuts out with ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus, and ha's a gift to preſerue large Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings to his owne purpoſes. Hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes the Reliques of Pride, and other mens ſuperfluities to his Abiſſe, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bord; whence is no Redemption, ſaue onely he reſerues ſome Trophees of his Trade, to match pieces of like valuation; indeed as Monuments for his Poſterity to make vſe of. Hee is a kinde of skip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſquey-legd Creature, keeps Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with Gentle men, and if you ſaw
<pb facs="tcp:2672:6"/>him at my Ladies, you would hold him ſome Vſher of a Dancing-ſchoole; as being apteſt in ſight for a Croſſe-Caper. By his clothes you might de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me him a Knight; but that, if you v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>caſe him, you will finde his S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Doublet nought but Fore-ſleeues and Breſt, the Backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part Buckeram; his Cloke and Cape of two ſorts, his Roſes and Garters of my Ladies old Cypres. His faſhion is to bring all out of faſhion; yet I weares the <hi>French</hi> were the onely People in the World, &amp; commonly deſires to ſpeake that Language aboue all. He vpholds in no Theeuerie to take what is brought, and ſtretch it forth to his beſt commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. His ſlender skill in Arithmeticke, (ouer and aboue his rules of Addition in a long Bill) has brought him to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this Maxime, that Diuiſion is moſt neceſſarie, and Participation a maine Particle of Thrift. In dead Vacations, he is not idle but oft practiz'd vpon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, where if a Sixe-foot creature
<pb facs="tcp:2672:7"/>chance to Perambulate to his Needles Point; at puſh of Pike hee either foiles, or in his Linſey-Wolſey Priſon enfolds them. His diſcourſe is rich and plentifull; the Argument hee treats on, new Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects; and tels ſtories of the neweſt, and Deuiſes your Court-Ladies haue got vp. He promiſes the Chamber-maid a new ſhagg-waſtcoate to induce her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to that moderne faſhion, not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his owne gaine; but to ſhew how well it might become her. Whether he bee in the Bookes of a fooliſh Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens Wife, or a fantaſtique Lady is to him alike materiall. If for the one hee make vp Gowne, Peticote, or other gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; hee vowes the Citizens carie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way now the only faſhion from Court-Ladies ſet off in light colours, gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, &amp;c. If for the other, contrarily hee ſweares your Citie Druggs now are not worth a ruſh; rich Embroyderies, Silkes, Taffaties, &amp;c. are moſt Lady-like, and in ſpeciall requeſt. He is an Ambo-dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb facs="tcp:2672:7"/>or Iacke of all ſides, and will needs mend that which God made. He is in this vaine Age much ſet by, for his qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie conſiſts of Inuention, and Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and can readily ſhape an Ape into all faſhions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> A Player,</head>
               <p>IS a Volume of various conceits or Epitome of Time, who by his repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation and appearance makes things long paſt ſeeme preſent. He is much like the Compters in Arithmeticke, and may ſtand one while for a King, another while a Begger, many times as a Mute or Cypher. Sometimes hee repreſents that which in his Life he ſcarſe practiſes, to be an honeſt Man. To the point, hee oft perſonates a Rorer, and therein comes neereſt to himſelfe. If his Action prefigure paſſion, he raues, rages, and proteſts much by his painted Heauens;
<pb facs="tcp:2672:8"/>and ſeemes in the heighth of this fit rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to pull <hi>Ioue</hi> out of the Garret, where perchance hee lies leaning on his el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowes, or is imployed to make Squips and Crackers to grace the Play. His Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience are often-times Iuducious; but his chiefe Admirers are commonly young wanton Chamber-maids, who are ſo taken with his poſture and gay clothes they neuer come to bee their owne women after. Hee exaſperates mens enormities, in publike view; and tels them their faults on the Stage, not as being ſorry for them, but rather wiſhes ſtill hee might finde more occaſions to worke on. He is the generall Corrupter of Spirits yet vntainted, inducing them by gradation to much laſciuious depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity. He is a Perſpicuity of vanity in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety; and ſuggeſts youth to perpetrate ſuch vices, as otherwiſe they had haply nere heard of. He is (for the moſt part) a notable Hypocrite, ſeeming what he is not, and is indeed what hee ſeemes not.
<pb facs="tcp:2672:8"/>And if hee loſe one of his fellow Stroules, in the Summer he turnes King of the Gipſies; if not, ſome great mans protection is a ſufficient Warrant for his peregrination, and a meanes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him the Towne-Hall; where hee may long exerciſe his qualitie, with clown-claps of great admiration in a Tone ſutable to the large Eares of his Illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate Auditorie. Hee is one ſeldome takes care for old Age; becauſe ill Diet and Diſorder, together with a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption or ſome worſe diſeaſe, taken vp in his full Careere; haue onely chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out his Cataſtrophe but to a Colon: and he ſcarſely ſuruiues to his naturall period of dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2672:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> A Country Shoo-maker,</head>
               <p>IS one, that ſeemes to haue ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight in Mens diſpoſitions, eſpecially of his ordinary Cuſtomers; for he will ſoon haue the length of your foote to an haire. Hee is not much vnlike ſome careleſſe Prelates; for he ſets a ſmooth face on the vpper Leather, but regards not the Soles ſlitting. His knowledge is meerely ſuperficiall, and diues much into the Art of excoriation. The But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher is the Prologue, or firſt branch of his profit: The Currier the intermedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um or Chorus: Himſelfe with the holpe of his cutting-knife, makes vp the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtrophe, in Boots, Shooes, Pantofles, &amp;c. Hee is an inueterate enemy to the liues of diuers dumbe beaſts, not caring how many are put to ſlaughter, ſo their Hides come cheaply to him. His Fox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furre pretending eaſe by drawing on; is
<pb facs="tcp:2672:9"/>the trueſt Embleme of his fraud and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ubtilty, intending rather to draw in for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is owne profit; and if you watch nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owly his inſteps in a darke ſhop; you may characterize him vttering (if not charging) Calfe for Neate. He is a great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ormentor of improfitable Cornes in a Common wealth; yet if you intreat him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ire, he is mercifull enough, and will at Laſt giue you eaſe. Hee is the crooked Toes Iavlor, and oft keepes Chamber-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ds ſo fine in their feete, they halt downe-right. In the Country he alway caries the Reliques of S. <hi>Hugh's</hi> Bones, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill the hot Sun-ſhine, conuerts him to Hay-making, or Harueſt-worke. In win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r ſeaſon you ſhall by 8 of the clocke, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ther finde his noſe ſteeled with a black <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot, then his Aule with a Briſtle. He is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruce fellow at a Faire, &amp; vſes Truncke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe at a Wake. He pinches more at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e groats then any other Trade at two-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nce. His skill is very raw in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ematicks; yet ha's taught many, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:2672:10"/>a while in his Leather priſon, to proue weather-wiſe; and by pricking and ſhooting of their Cornes perfectly ſenſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le of ſtormes enſuing. His greateſt enemie is a Rich man with the goute, who neuer weares ought but ſlippers in all companies. Hee tels you the onely Court faſhion is to walke in Bootes, and ſweares they are the compleateſt orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of legge or foote. His maine feare is a Parliament, leſt there might proceed ſome new addition to the laſt Act, to thwart his deſignes, That as Butchers were forbad to ſell meat on Sundayes, ſo he ſhould ſhooes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which if it happen, he vowes neither King nor Begger, ſhall paſſe his pinching iuriſdiction ſo long as he vpholds the Trade. Briefly, he i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one vſes leaſt conſcience on Sundayes when if your neceſſities bring you to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhop doore, hee will bee ſure to rac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> two pence or a groat more on the prie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for comming ſo vnſeaſonably. He ſing all the Rounds and Catches that <hi>Robi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2672:10"/>
                  <hi>hood</hi> had; and the Pinder of <hi>Wakefield</hi> is commonly the fore-horſe of his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. He deemes good-Ale the onely vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder of a cleare voyce, and wiſhes, that he which loues it not may neuer ſing more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>4.</hi> A Rope-Maker,</head>
               <p>IS the Lobſters Executor, and gets his liuing contrary to all men; he holds by that as a maine end of his liuing, which catching hold on another proues fatall to his deſtruction; howbeit hee ſeemes Cowardly, and retires fearefully, as if he were working out his owne De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinie. He is like ſome hypocriticall Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, that lookes toward charitie, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tires ſtill to couetouſneſſe. Or by his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of going back-ward when he looks forward; may claime affinity with the waterman, who rowes one way, yet lookes another. He is the Spider that
<pb facs="tcp:2672:11"/>ſpins from about his owne bowels his three-fold web, which may afterward intrap ſome ſilly Flies of misfortune. His Boy that ſits ſtill turning the wheele; (but for default of grauity) may expreſly reſemble the old Vſurer turning and winding his money; himſelfe the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney-maſter or Broker that goes vp and downe, twiſting vp the whole eſtate to his owne Commodity. His wares are of ſeuerall ſizes, ſome great, ſome ſmaller; and the Beadle finds his as ſutable to an Whores backe, as the Hangman his to a Theefes necke. His Anceſtors ſurely were Gardiners or Field-keepers, and he deriues his Pedegree from the Hemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalke. Hee ſcarſly knowes his owne Coat-Armes; but may be informed as followeth: On the borders or out-skirts of a faire field Argent, in midſt of a three-turning High-way paſſant, three maie wooden pillars, with croſſe banes, in ſhape of a Triangle, three faire Hemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalks vprearing from the foote of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:2672:11"/>Pillars, and entwining the body in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of a Vine: then three Collers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicularly deſcending; with nooſes of equall diſtance. A croſſe cheuron of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in the middle and vttermoſt part, and in the midſt of the maine Scutcheon two Beaters with heau'd Beetles. The Creſt a large bottome of round platted pack-thred, in ſhape of a Turkes Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, and two Porters for the Suppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters girt with a Trinodie of Ropes, and alike croſſed ouer the ſhoulders in forme of a Belt. To be ſerious, hee is a man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious in his calling, and his backe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyring, brings him on more forward in the world. He is the Saylors hope-hold; for he cannot ride ſafely, without his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry. In fine he is conſtant to his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and lets not ſlip his good occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, till at length the cord of his life vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twines and hee returnes to his graue, where we leaue him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2672:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>5:</hi> A Smith,</head>
               <p>IS a man principally compos'd of two Elements, Fire and ſtrong Liquor; his dreames are oft Iron bars, Steel-gads Wedges and Thunderbolts, and hee maintaines his Antiquity from <hi>Vulcan.</hi> He vpholds Warres the onely trade at Sea, and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lfare of the Land, and brags no man can liue without him, deeming it moſt requiſite himſelfe ſhould be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Pariſh, and King of all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions; according to the old verſe,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By Hammer and hand, all Arts do ſtand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hee is the morning Cocke, and the euening Hogge; for hee alway begins well, and continues in the fire Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-like, till in the afternoone, when hee comes to his Liquor, and ha's taken his load, can ſcarſe ſee to driue one naile
<pb facs="tcp:2672:12"/>right. He is the Horſe-Phyſitian, the Plow-mans right hand, the Sea-mans ſtay, and the Generals Commander. His Hammer frames ſpeeches to the clouds, ſo loudly, that he rends the Ayre, teares the Earth, and brings downe the talleſt Cedars. He grieues more at the death of a good Gelding, then many men doe at their wiues Funerall. He ha's euer an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to trauell to <hi>Peru,</hi> to ſee horſes ſhod with gold; but could neuer get ſiluer to begin his iourney. He neuer ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries enuy in his breſt to his Maſter, but payes an ill turne vpon his Beaſt. Hee neuer rides with Bootes but when <hi>Skimmington</hi> keeps Holiday, and then a ruſty Sword keeps warme his ſides. He is a man moſt apt at barganing, for hee commonly ſtrikes while the Iron's hot. He is no leſſe ingenuous then induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; for he is ſtill hammering on ſome ſubiect or other. The greateſt harme hee ha's done in the Common wealth, is his puffing of Sea-coale to ſo high a Price;
<pb facs="tcp:2672:13"/>for by his ordinary vſe, hee ha's raiſed them to extraordinary rate. His head is oft too heauy for his heeles, for hee dreames of Ringals, Spauins, and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and ſeemes to haue more skill in this kinde then the beſt Doctor. He is a well experienc'd Horſe-Phlebotomiſt; and to miniſter a Drench, ha's his Oxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne alwayes in readineſſe. He is neuer vnfurniſht of his Bath or Lotium-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which has beene euer a moſt appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceipt for the Itch or Scabd hands. He ha's heard <hi>Markhams</hi> Method twice read ouer; and had <hi>Markham</hi> but known his ſecrets hee had rode in his foot-cloth long ſince. He ha's found out a new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe, to make Bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s for Warre-horſe, to ore-runne the Enemy; and had hee but coale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Iron gratis, he would make an Iron inſtrument ſhould charge and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge 500 Muskets with one man. His great Grand-father was an Iriſh-man, and ſuckt the blood of beaſts; himſelfe more <hi>Engliſh</hi> bred and leaues it to the
<pb facs="tcp:2672:13"/>hogs and dogs. His buckler is a browne Apron, and his weapon a Hammer. He Anuils out his oathes and curſes in fury like ſparks from a plow-ſhare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>6.</hi> A Tobacconiſt,</head>
               <p>IS a man furious, making all ſmoke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine where hee comes, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe may proue a ſtout ſouldier in a Towne where long ſiege hath made ſcarſitie of victuals; for hee moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly preferres ſmoke-drinke before ſmok-meat. At firſt he is haply brought to vſe it, but for faſhion-ſake, vntill cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome make it habituall: His Brain-pan is lined like an old Vſurers Night-cap; and for his Belly, though it make a faire ſhew outwardly; yet there are many ſluttiſh corners within. The Plurifie, Gout, and other diſeaſes are to him as inſeparable, as oppreſſion to an Vſurer, or griping to a Broker. The Recorder,
<pb facs="tcp:2672:14"/>Flute, Hob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe or any other Pipe the beſt Muſician can inuent, doth yeeld him ſuch content as doth the Tobacco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipe; or can afford him like Muſicke to pleaſe his Noſtrils; were it the Oaten Reed of that Rurall Shepheard which ſo ſweetly warbl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d on the Plaines of of <hi>Arcadie.</hi> Of all other Countries <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is leaſt beholding to him; for hee prefers <hi>Verina, Trinidado,</hi> and other bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Parts before it, as being the beſt Seed-plots of thoſe Drugges hee moſt affects. In all companies where hee comes, hee is neuer vnfurniſh'd of his caſe of Inſtruments, which he will bee ready to draw on any occaſion for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe or his friend; and hath his ſtops ready at his ſingers ends to make his Limbecke burne more feruently, till all be conſum'd to aſhes. To conclude, he is a man diſſolues himſelfe in vapors while he liues, and being dead is fit for none but Chirurgions to make vſe of. On whom I will beſtow this Epitaph.</p>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2672:14"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Here lyes one tooke all in ſnuffe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whoſe life was but a Bubble:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Now being dead, hee's calme enough,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And's friends are rid of trouble.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>7.</hi> A Cunning woman,</head>
               <p>IS the female ſpawne engendred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene a Chyrurgion and a Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and would ſeeme to haue skill equal, eſpecially when ſhe meetes with them who either beleeue or admire her. Her proceeding ſhee neuer tooke in the Schooles; for her learning is more na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, and came indeed of her Mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wit; ſodered vp heere and there with ſome fragments of obſeruation gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from goſſippings and diſcourſe with others of her ſocietie. Her Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients (though for ſeuerall diſeaſes) doe neuer much differ; a few pounded Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpillers, a roſted Bitches marrow, Staueſaker, a little Bores-greaſe and
<pb facs="tcp:2672:15"/>Quick-ſiluer, theſe are all to a Dramme; of which (with a few ſimples) ſhee can temper you a ſalue for euery ſore, and performe as great Cures as euer did <hi>Galen</hi> or <hi>Hypocrates.</hi> If it happen ſhe be called into queſtion by Authority, ſhee (like the Snaile) creeps into her ſhell, and either hides herſelfe out of the way, or elſe brings in ſome of her ſufficientſt Neighbours to teſtifie for her what great good ſhee hath done in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth. After a while that ſhee is growne thus perfectly cunning to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the world by her Phyſicke; ſhee haply proceeds further, preſuming to profeſſe the Black-Art, and will make you beleeue ſhe ha's the ſtarres at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and can readily helpe you to any thing you haue loſt; prouided you mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſomething vnto her to finde her ſelfe. If you would know what ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide you in your affaires, let her but looke in your Hand, or perfectly on your face, her skill is ſo exquiſite in phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiognomie
<pb facs="tcp:2672:15"/>or palmiſtry, ſhee will eaſily ſatisfie your demands without ſcruple. Shee is firſt cozen to your Gypſies for Fortune-telling, and can with as much dexterity coozen you of your money, while ſhee onely pretends obſeruing lines in your Palme. In breefe, ſhe is one ſo ſeeming skilfull in many things, that indeed ſhe ha's iudgement in nothing; but one that by her iugglyng Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtures ſeekes not onely to delude the world, but depraue men of that worthy calling and profeſſion, to whom much honour is due. And ſo I leaue her, as I finde her, a Subiect vnworthy my fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcourſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2672:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>8</hi> A Cobler,</head>
               <p>IS a man neuer like to be prefer'd by his worke-manſhip, for that right terme makes him an excellent worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. He reſembles moſt fitly an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worme liuing vnder a ſtall; for he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly keepes a little ſhop vnder a great one. Hee is a fellow ſo neceſſary in a Common-wealth, that few can be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him; for if any happen to ſtep awry, he is ſtraight ready to ſet them vpright. Hee is one, though apt enough to take his liquor, farre better then the common drunkard; for he mends euery day, and houre; yet contrary to all, is neuer on the mending hand on Sunday<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hee is moſt commonly a good Singer, good fellow, and a Iolly talker. Hee ſleepes more ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cure then any man, and neuer feares fire, and like a crooked Crauiſh, pray s the cleane contrary way: Others pray for faire, he for foule weather. He
<pb facs="tcp:2672:16"/>brags that himſelfe nor none of his were neuer knowne Bankrupts. He ſets vp his Trade for ſix-pence, ſcarſe euer truſts twelue-pence, and can command the beſt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n in the Towne to ſtay his leyſure. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> holds a Smi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h, a man moſt vnneceſſary in a Common-wealth; it goes to his heart to ſee an iron-heele patch, or a hobnayle ſhooe. He is much vext at the vent of Sparrow-bils, and can as ill away with f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhion of woodden Clamps, as being maine obſtacles to his profeſſion. He ſhould by ſome appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances ſeeme an excellent linguiſt, for he his much inur'd with Tranſlation. His Thumbe and his Tongue are the beſt Inſtruments hee makes vſe of, and the more hee employes them, the better his wife is pleaſed, and the Conſort more tunable. In fine he is a ſtubbed fellow well briſtled, and being arm'd with a welſh-hook'd knife, or ſharpe ſemite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, rips vp before you many old matters, and brings Aule at Laſt to his own ends.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2672:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>9.</hi> A Tooth-drawer,</head>
               <p>IS a man highly fain'd for his Art; for he got it beyond the Seas, as by La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels at his doore may appeare. As thus: Know all gentlemen, that I Signior or Mounſieur ſuch a one, after long tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, and greet experience in forraigne parts, beyond the Seas, haue induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly attained many rare ſecrets, viz. To draw Teeth, ſet in New, mundifie or make blacke Teeth white, rid the gummes, or take away the paine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out drawing; nor doth hee reſt heere, but if need require profeſſes the Cure of many other diſeaſes, as Cramp, Convulſions, Gouts, Palſies, Catars, &amp;c. And can tell them at firſt ſight, if they be curable or not. Howbeit, this ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall view muſt bring him ſome feeling, elſe he is not well pleaſed. His buſineſſe is neuer perform'd in ſo much State, as
<pb facs="tcp:2672:17"/>when he is mounted vpon his Palfrey or Iriſh Hobby, riding through the high ſtreets of the City, like <hi>Caeſar</hi> in his Triumph, his Clyents following him laying their hands on their mouthes, as though they would keepe ſilence, till paine makes them roare out, which his horſe or he perceiuing, reflects backe on them an eye of ruthfull pitie, ſtraight playes the Conſtables part to bid them come after him; and hauing felt their pulſes, lookes next into their mouthes, to know their age, thruſts in his hand or fingers, and ſeemes in this poſture a <hi>Richard Corde-Lyon,</hi> diuing to the heart or ſtump of hollow Teeth. Yet haue I heard he ha's a tricke to conuey an iron punch in a hand-kerchiefe, which oft proue the ieopardy of a iaw to ſome of his Patients. He is a fellow very capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; for hee is apt to twit you in the Teeth on the leaſt occaſion; exceeding deſperate, for if you take diſtaſte or finde your ſelfe agreeu'd, though it bee
<pb facs="tcp:2672:18"/>but a Tooth-aking, hee is ſtraight ready to draw. He is the mouths Gardiner, that prunes the hedge-rowes of the Teeth, and like a Serg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant military ſet them in their due Rankes and Files. Thoſe rott<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ged and corrupt Teeth he ha's drawne from others haue beene the onely meanes to draw in him cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomers; and hee preſerues them as Trophes of Triumph to dignifie his B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nner. At ſpre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ding forth his Flags of affiance, ſtreamer, Pendants, &amp;c. multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of people commonly aſſemble; when the Cut-purſe ſpying his beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage, becomes a great ſharer in the worke, and can as nimbly imploy his limetwig-fingers to draw a Purſe, as himſelfe a Tooth. Of all Trades in the City, he is moſt beholding to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ker; for hee and his Confections haue beene a great bane to the Teeth, helpt him to much worke, and brought ſowre ſawce to their ſweete meats. To conclude hee is a man onely vſ'd at a
<pb facs="tcp:2672:18"/>pinch; and the vſe of his pincers h 's drawne his Patients out of patience. Thoſe that haue once t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ide him, hope they ſhall neuer haue occaſion to vſe him more. So I leaue him, till paine pricks me to employ him, but deſire no further acquaintance of him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>10.</hi> A Tinker,</head>
               <p>IS a rude ruſtick ruffe hayr'd Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, one that ſeldome walkes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Pike-ſtaffe, a Doxy and a Dogge. He is ſecond coſen to <hi>Vulcan,</hi> approues his genealogy from <hi>Tubal-Cain,</hi> rather of <hi>Cain</hi> then <hi>Tubal.</hi> His ſhop is alwayes at his backe, and he gets his liuing by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of holes; for he ſeldome ſtops one vnleſſe ſix more beare him Company. He deſires moſt to be a free holder vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Common: his houſe neuer knew the blacke Bible, but the blacke Pot is his neereſt and deareſt friend.
<pb facs="tcp:2672:19"/>His wife hee ſeldome regards, but makes it the chiefeſt holiday when hee leaſt ſees her. In the ſummer ſeaſon he is moſt frequent to be ſeene at the Royall Exchange of a Buſh or hedge, where he commonly dynes vpon an earthen Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in the winter ſtowes himſelfe in ſome muſty Barne. His complexion is ſanguine, and he deemes the Barber-no fit member in a Common wealth. His prayers are, The diuell take me, or, God refuſe me. In his talke, his full points are curſes, and his firſt line o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thes, where af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he hath rapped out ſome twenty or fortie, hee beginnes to ſweare, and hee tels you hee is ſeldome let blood in the face, or his Noſe naild on with his wiues fingers. He is one that haunts Wakes and Faires like a ſpirit, and his Muſicke is alwayes a paire of woodden Organs vnder a Peinthouſe, or a Croſſe which he loues not to ſee; beſide his daily practiſe of the voyce ſet and ſung to the Tabering on a Ket<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle.
<pb facs="tcp:2672:19"/>He exclaimes much againſt Glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and wiſhes euery Butchers ſhoppe were turned to an Alehouſe. He loues not to go vpon Plantages, vnleſſe it bee where euery houſe hath a Brew-houſe belonging to it. He paies his Land-lords rent with blowes and curſes, becauſe his houſe is not tenantable; for hee'l bring the Doore rather then want fine. Hee holds <hi>Banbury</hi> to be a place not to bee pitti'd though in neuer ſo much miſery. His heart is as hard as his hammer, his fingers ſmell like Bird-lime. He thinkes a Knaue, a Drunkard, and a Tinker to be the beſt Common-wealths men and to make moſt ſtirring, of which hee deſires he may haue an Inheritance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2672:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>11.</hi> A Fidler,</head>
               <p>IS a Baſtard of the Muſes; one that by early riſing and la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e watching ſcrapes out a poore liuing; for he is wakefull as the Belman, and many times after two or three houres earneſt looking vp for reward is c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owned with a Piſpot. If you would know of any merry mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or Feaſting, follow but him, and you cannot miſſe the way; hee ha's ſtill the beſt in elligence of them all You may perceiue by the Roſemary and Ribbon in his hat where he was the laſt Sunday, nor can the Clarks booke bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter certifie you who was the Bride and Brideſgroome; himſelfe being there a man of greateſt Requeſt. At any Faire, Wake, May pole rearing, or Whitſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ale, you ſhall rarely want his company, but finde him alway in readineſſe to bid you welcome; And if haply ſome ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous
<pb facs="tcp:2672:20"/>Gentleman lye in his way, hee will not miſſe to giue him his mornings ſalutation, be he ſtranger, or otherwiſe: he ha's his name or ſtile as ready in his mouth, as if hee had beene his old ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance or neereſt kinne. His skill by the eare is much in the ſounds and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent tones of muſicke, yet ſtands beſt affected to the chinking of money. Hee may for his impudence reſemble moſt fitly the Tongue of a Iewes-trumpe; which though oft repulſt by the finger, returnes with more eagerneſſe to his full Twang. His fingers are ſo pliant to his Inſtrument, that though hee chance to ſcrew his head backwards into a pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle pot, yet forgets not his leſſon, but by rote plods forward in his play. His Boy is the ſweete ſinging Birde hung forth at a Tauerne doore next the ſtreete, that proffers his notes to all p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngers. He trauerſes all Companies, feeds on all ſorts of dyet, receiues all mens gratui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. If his largeſſe come off lamely, hee
<pb facs="tcp:2672:21"/>goes forth of your company with a grand grumble more baſe then his Viol; If largely, his Kitt and he iogge away merrily together. When hee gets but ſome Songs or Sonnets patcht vp with Kibaldrie, or enterlarded with any thing againſt the ſtate, they are maine helps to him, and he will aduenture to ſing them though they coſt him a whipping for his labour. His head is troubled with many Crotchets, and hee oft ſtriues to ſtraine his ſtrings a note beyond Ela; till many times both cracke together. If he chance to get a Liuery on his backe of ſome noble perſonage, he is well worthy your entertainement, and you muſt pay to his Coate. You cannot anger him worſe, then by telling him of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors grace, and ſhould you repeat but a line, his melody would conuert to a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady. Yet hee may haply beare out that or any thing, for his quality with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of knocks and rough language, ha's arm'd him for Battry and an Aſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſ
<pb facs="tcp:2672:21"/>ination. To conclude, he is a man neuer much reſpected, though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pted in mens companies: and then better heard then ſeene.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>12.</hi> A cunning Horſe-Courſer,</head>
               <p>IS a perſon ſo altogether compact of a Country habit, that hee loues not a blacke hat: A skilfull Farrier is his friends enemy. Hee reads <hi>Markhams</hi> Method, and <hi>Banks</hi> is his old acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. He keeps his beſt horſes in the worſt clothes, and his worſt Iades bee richeſt on weeke-dayes. He hath the Racers, Breeds, and Clymats of the beſt in <hi>England;</hi> for variety of <hi>Barbary, Spaniſh, Engliſh, Flaunders</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> breed, his race, his hunting, drawing, or all in one if you pleaſe. Of his baſtard ſort the Sire and Damme hee keepes an exact Catalogue, and freely offers to let you haue the triall of him any morning
<pb facs="tcp:2672:22"/>to Hye-gate; and ten to one hee will ſpend ſo much time to ride with you himſelfe, where haply his Copers bee before to carry him backe vpon ſome new bargaine; but ere you get to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> you are catcht in his fet-locks, and he faſtens on you a Iade that dare not clim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hye-gate hill. Hee is a man not much affected with Pride, but makes commonly his prauncing ſerue as a Prologue to his profit He trots, ambles, gallops, rebounds and treads the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in all varietie of Paces: hee cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumuents Smithfield with curuets, and leaps madly through thicke and thinne, ſeeming in his full careere, ready to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrip <hi>Pegaſus.</hi> He keeps at all Faires in Country habits, and the change of his clothes is as frequent as the Moones. He prefers a ſtout horſe before a ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne wife, and with more delight ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages the one then the other. If a luſty Courſer come to his hand, his beaſt and he muſt trace the prime ſtreets of the
<pb facs="tcp:2672:22"/>City; for his viſit is Cheap-ſide, Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall, Watling, ſtreet, &amp;c. Being thus mounted, hee beginnes to eleuate his voyce in a lofty Tone ſet by himſelf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and can ſpeake no other language on his backe but 100. Angels, which oft he ſhould haue beene bleſt with from ſuch and ſuch a Knight, and this the onely beaſt that makes him rich, for hee won at leaſt 7 Races in ſix weekes. What he ſwears and lyes hee has vouchers for, and the beſt remedy you can haue, if he proue a Iade, is, that you neuer take him for an honeſt man. But leaue him as he is, till he mend his manners.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>13.</hi> Bethlem.</head>
               <p>IS a place of reſt for reſtleſſe perſons, where though many meet and all of one Nation, yet ſhow ſeuerall conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. You may haply heare a confuſed hubbub of contrariety in their ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb facs="tcp:2672:23"/>yet many times harpe vpon ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that men more ſenſible then themſelues may make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe of. It is a place where many a ſtout heart has beene tamed &amp; brought vnder. Where this houſe is, ſcarce any need aske, yet may it in ſome ſort ſeeme queſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and this Theame challenge a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger comment then ordinary; for but well conſider, and we ſhall finde many bedlems elſe-where, as in Court, City, Country, Vniuerſity, &amp;c. Are there not Court Bedlems, that conforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues meerely to all formes of new fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions, that expend time to raiſe vp a puffe-paſte honour, which as childr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns bubbl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niſh immediate, irr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>couera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or bring in the cataſtrophe a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracefull p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aecipitation. Citie B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dlems that ſeeming cautelous, proue oft too credulous, and by giuing much credit to others themſelues haue none left; or contrary rake and ſcrape together they know not what for they know not
<pb facs="tcp:2672:23"/>whom. Country Bedlems that haue ſold their Farmes to buy them a Pede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and at laſt left themſelues no Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony. Vniuerſity Bedlems, that haue ſtudied their Maiors, Minors, Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Conſequent to bee at length concluded Coxecombs. This place therefore is not onely confin'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene More fields and Biſhopſgate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreete, but may proue more ample in extent then the King hath any Land.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>14.</hi> Ludgate.</head>
               <p>IS the maine Prop, or ſureſt vpholder of Ancient Citizens, who are decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the Nominatiue of credit to the Vocatiue of Caret; hauing multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>latiue, Subſtracted in the Ablatiue. The Citie is the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, this the Center, or as the Foxe ſaid by the Furriers ſhoppe the ſureſt place to meete in. It is a Receptacle of
<pb facs="tcp:2672:24"/>Complainers againſt dead vacations, who haue perhaps made vp their cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophe in the quick'ſt Terme. It is the reſting place or cares and troubles, a full poyſe of miſery or ſafe harbour of ill husbandry. It is a kinde of Inns of Court, where men gather more by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience then ſtudy, and haue the Law at their fingers ends. The Keepers in it reſemble Aſhen trees, bearing fruit, which they turne to no mens profit but their owne; and ſeeme to haue power to open and ſhut to all vnder their charge, as thoſe that receiue Keyes from S. <hi>Peter:</hi> for you ſhall perceiue them no leſſe skilfull in the ſounds and ſtops of each then the moſt curious and beſt Muſitian. They are men of much cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection, and looke more warily to their ſeuerall wards then the cunning'ſt Fencer, preſt to play his Maſters-prize. Shortly, it is a houſe ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ier pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas'd then kept, and a mans great'ſt Fine is payd at parting. It is the
<pb facs="tcp:2672:24"/>Bankrouts bait, which at firſt he gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily ſwallowes, after is ſwallowed vp of. The Speed-well neuer winters here, but the Hope-well ha's caſt Anchor.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>16.</hi> Bridewell.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BRideſ-well,</hi> or <hi>Bridgets well,</hi> is the City Schoole-miſtris, that by due correction tames and brings vnder her vnruly obſtinate children of both ſexes; thoſe that haue dranke, or inde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d but throughly taſted of this well, will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly euer after bee moſt cautelous of any relapſe to returne thither for a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cure. It is a faire, free, hoſpitable open houſe for all commers. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of Gueſts hither inuited or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther incited, ſeemes quite contrary to that of common Innes, where fault is moſt found for want of obſeruance, the diſtaſte here growing of more fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers then needs: Howbeit their At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants,
<pb facs="tcp:2672:25"/>(as perſons well deſeruing) are men in Liueries, Beadles in Blue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coates, who hold as much land by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing out ſtatute lace, as your Boſomes-Inne Cariers by deliuering cheeſes at Chriſtmas: They are ready waiters on your backs on any occaſion, and their maine ſeruice a full ſatiety of whipping-cheare. They are men not fluent in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, yet captious in your company, much inclined to criticiſme, and ſo Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyricall, that on the le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt fault commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted they are ready to giue you a Ierke. They much reſemble the Momuſſes of our times, aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cted with the ſpirit of Detraction; onely in this different, their hands rather then tongues are the greateſt Back-biters. Their beſt exerciſe is running and driuing at a Carts Taile; where they take as much pride in the poſture and practiſe of their weapon, as a dexterious Fencer before a Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny at <hi>Symon</hi> and <hi>Iude,</hi> and are no leſſe bountifull and free in the open Markets, then at their owne Hall Table. They
<pb facs="tcp:2672:25"/>are men of large Commiſſion, exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue in iuriſdiction to the vtmoſt part of their Regiment, euen from the Whore rampant, to the poore Rogue couchant, and are as cunning in conueyances and ſlights as a Iugler; for hee is no more but Whip, Paſſe, and Be gon; yet theſe are neuer out of action. It is an Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dammicall Conuenticle, tranſlated on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Clime; or an hotch-potch of people different in Age, Sexe, Nation, Diſpoſition, not ſeldome in Religion; yet euery one vſes that little conſcience he has, ſo farre as the whip will giue him leaue. Not vnlike the Family of Loue, for they haue here all things in common, which I thinke commonly is little or nothing, vnleſſe the Whip, Stocks, or Pillory. You haue here the grand groſſe Baud, Prouocatious Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, vngratious Letcher, audacious Whore, vngracious Kaue; rude Ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fians, Runnagates, Cheates, Pimps, Nips, Foyſts, Decoyes, <hi>&amp; multa alia quae nunc, &amp;c.</hi> And though it be euery
<pb facs="tcp:2672:26"/>weeke ſwept ouer by the Beeſome of authority, yet is this muck-hill repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed daily with ſtuffe of the like kinde. It is a Bee-hiue of Drones, where the good ſting them home to the old a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode, a Pill to purge vagabonds out of the Common-wealth, and a Curry-combe for Hackney whores to reduce them to their priſtine reputation; for if after puniſhment you ſo chance to call them, they get you on the hip, and haue the Law on their owne ſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. It is a well compacted Common-wealth of workers againſt their wils, where the awe of the whipſtocke confines them to the laborious ſtroke of the hempe-blocke, and the turning of the wheele a daily Memento of turning ouer a new leafe. It is a bit or bridle for Roaring Boyes that flye out beyond their bounds, or a ciuill gouernment of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in behauiour moſt vnciuill, where, though many meet roughly all ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, yet here grow calme enough and worke together like neighbours. It is a
<pb facs="tcp:2672:26"/>Receptacle of Rogues, Ruffians and Runnagates, who neuer ſerue God but on Saturday mornings, and then call on him but with ſmall deuotion: when the ſtorme is ouer, all is ſalu'd vp with a ſob and a ſoure face. It is a ſtepdame to ſtubborne natures who would neuer bee ruled by their more naturall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: An Empericke in a diſeaſed cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, that by a skilfull Phlebotomy, with well managing of a ſmall knotted whipcord, ha's preſeru'd many from the fare of a hard hempen halter, and clenſed both City &amp; Suburbs of much corruption. It may not vnfitly bee ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Trades Increaſe, or Cities Hope-well, where her ſtubborne youth are made wieldy, brought vp in handi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft profeſſions. It is the Reall Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of good houſwiues, whither they commonly reſort for their Hemp, Flaxe, or Towe, and here finde it ready beaten to their hands by thoſe, who haply thought little to haue come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Iuriſdiction of Blocke and Beetle.</p>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2672:27"/>
                  <head>The tenor of the new Law.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All graceleſſe wights that lead Luxurious liues,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bold roaring Boyes, baſe Queanes, &amp; vnchaſt wiues,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cutpurſes, Canters, Cheaters, Hie-way-ſtanders,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bawdes, Bouncing-Megs, Decoyes, Puncks, Pimps and Panders</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All vagrant <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>agabonds o'th Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo wealth,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sharks, Prigs, Nips, Foyſts, that pill and liue by ſtealth;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whole ſwarmes of lazy Drones in corners lurking,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That rather chooſe to hang then fall to working:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſe with their carſt confederates, all muſt ſtand</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Toth' new laws Iudgement, that doth ſtrait command</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>An equall pennance for their crime moſt meet,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That (yoakt in Carts) they now muſt purge the ſtreet</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of noyſome Garbage, carry Dirt and Dung;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Beadles following with a mighty throng;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whilſt as they paſſe the people ſcoffing ſay,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Holla, ye pampred Iades of Aſia.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The knotty Whip could neuer halfe ſo ſling yee</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As this new law; the very ſhame will bring yee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>(If euer) now to mend, elſe ſtill ye muſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Driue, till ye ſweat agen in Dirt and Duſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bare fac'd in publike view throughout the City;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>While all men laugh, and few or none will pitty:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iuſt is that law, whoſe ſentence thus inforces</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All thoſe who liu'd as Beaſts, to draw like Horſes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2672:27"/>To conclude, it is the latter courſe of a full Banquet ſerued in Sallets and ſharpe Tarts, or the ſowre ſauce to the ſweet meats of Venery. It is a Diet-drinke moſt wholeſome for a Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monger, or a principall receit for the Itch of concupiſcence. In fine a free Hoſpitall for the Remedie of ſundry diſeaſes, whither many are brought, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cure purg'd and paſt away: the lazy Drones from Idleneſſe, lewde Letchers from Luxury, vaine vnthrifts from Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digalitie, old perſons from vildneſſe, youth from wildneſſe, all if poſſible to goodneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Whence if any depart and mend not, an hund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed to one they drop into the Hangmans Budget.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>16.</hi> New-gate.</head>
               <p>IS the old way to an ill Deſtinie, or the Hye-way to looke through a hempen window. It is the Blacke-dogs
<pb facs="tcp:2672:28"/>walke of an ill conſcience, and the period of a Purloyner. It is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burbs of hell, and not ſeldome vnder the Iuriſdiction of Furies. It is a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Helleſpont, wherein many ſetting forth are ſhip wrackt in their iourney. It is a darke Cell of care, and dungeon of deſpaire, a place that ſends all worſe forth, and ſcarſe any mend. It is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuous rabble of Rogues, Villaines, and Whores, where if once they paſſe the fiery triall they ſoone grow maſter; they loue not to ride, and euer feare the changing of the Moone. All good deeds of charity, they turne to ſinne and wickedneſſe: The Tapſters purſe, and the Tobacco-ſhop is their Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and hee that ſweares and drinkes moſt is of beſt reſpect: The ſtouteſt Rogue ha's there moſt credit, and the cunningſt foyſt wins beſt eſteeme. All ill is the higheſt ayme, and he that hath beene longeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heeuart is the worſt member, keepes the remembrance.
<pb facs="tcp:2672:28"/>booke and is growne a Schoole-maſter fit for the Diuell; ſo abſolute a Rogue that hee growes in office to ſee ſinne correct vice. Hee ſummons Iuries, Iudges, and can tell fortunes to all commers. He has a Title ſutable to his diſpoſition, and goes vnder the name of Corporall Craft. Briefly, it is a Cage of vncleane Birds, a Coope of Cony-catchers, and an Abiſſe of all Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
